Finding Aid for the Japanese American Research Project Collection about Japanese in the U.S. (Yuji Ichioka papers) LSC.2010.00
UCLA Library Special Collections
Japanese American Research Project (Yuji Ichioka) collection of material about Japanese in the United States
1893-1973
UCLA Library Special Collections
Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles)
LSC.2010.00
401 linear feet (760 boxes, 21 cartons, 1 oversize folder)
Collection consists of materials collected by the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) related to the history of Japanese and Japanese Americans in the United States. Contains more than 100 groups of personal papers related to individuals and/or families, and these groups contain correspondence, diaries, photographs, and a variety of printed materials. Also contains several thousand returned questionnaires and records related to surveys of the Issei, Nisei, and Sansei conducted during the 1960s. Also includes over 400 tape recordings and oral histories, original art work done by internees during WWII, yearbooks, directories, newspapers, pamphlets, and records related to Japanese consulates on the West Coast. The collection also contains administrative records of the Japanese American Research Project.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. For information about the access status of the material that you are looking for, refer to the Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Japanese American Research Project, 1973.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942332103606533
History
The Japanese American Research Project (originally named the Issei History Project) was initiated by Wakamatsu Shigeo, President of the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) in 1960. The three major objectives of the project were: to conduct a sociological survey based on a national sampling of the Issei and Nisei populations; to publish a definitive history of the Japanese Americans; and to collect documents, including oral history and memorabilia. UCLA agreed to co-sponsor the project along with the JACL.
T. Scott Miyakawa became the first director of the project, and Robert A. Wilson was appointed to administer the fund. Later funds were contributed to the project to include the Sansei generation in the survey.
[Survey Parameters]
to conduct a sociological survey based on a national sampling of the Issei and Nisei populations
to publish a definitive history of the Japanese Americans
and to collect documents, including oral history and memorabilia. UCLA agreed to co-sponsor the project along with the JACL.
T. Scott Miyakawa became the first director of the project, and Robert A. Wilson was appointed to administer the fund. Later funds were contributed to the project to include the Sansei generation in the survey.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials collected by the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) related to the history of Japanese and Japanese Americans in the United States. Contains more than 100 groups of personal papers related to individuals and/or families, and these groups contain correspondence, diaries, photographs, and a variety of printed materials. Also contains several thousand returned questionnaires and records related to surveys of the Issei, Nisei, and Sansei conducted during the 1960s. Also includes over 400 tape recordings and oral histories, original art work done by incarcerees during WWII, yearbooks, directories, newspapers, pamphlets, and records related to Japanese consulates on the West Coast. The collection also contains administrative records of the Japanese American Research Project.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Personal papers
Materials relating to the Japanese consulates in the United States
Organizational materials
Materials relating to Japanese language schools
Materials relating to incarceration camps and World War II
Published materials (not included in previous categories)
Photographs and photo albums
Oral history tapes
Issei, Nisei, and Sansei survey returns and related office files
Miscellaneous items
Frank F. Chuman papers (see separate finding aid)
Sumitomo Bank of California
Nisei and Sansei survey, original returns
University of Hawaii at Manoa - transcripts of oral history interviews
W. Eugene Dimon papers (see separate finding aid)
Arai Family papers (Collection 1254)
Shigeichi Kawano papers (Collection 1251)
Siberius Y. Saito drawings
Related Materials
Collection of papers from the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs dealing with Japanese emigration into the United States and other countries (microform). Available at UCLA Library, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Japanese oral histories, 1964-1969 (ACCN 0806). Available at Special Collections, J. Willard Marriott Library, The University of Utah.
Scrapbooks.; Paintings (visual works).; Photograph albums.; Japanese Americans -- United States -- History; Japanese American families -- Archives.; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Schools, Japanese -- United States.; Periodicals.; Diaries.; Audiotapes.; Family papers.; Drawings.; Photographs.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles)--Archives.; United States. War Relocation Authority.
- Personal Papers
  - Abiko Papers, ca. 1968; 1 folder
    Scope and Contents note
    Yasuo William Abiko. Nisei. Publisher, Nichibei Jiji [Nichibei Times], San Francisco.
    General note
    [see also Abiko family papers (Collection 1690) ]
    - Brief Story of the Life of Kyutaro Abiko., ca. 1968; (Manuscript, 15pp. Photocopy, 3 items) (Box 159, Folder 1)
  - Akahori Family Papers, ca. 1908-1965; 21.0 linear ft.
    Masaru Akahori was born in 1884 in Tokushima Prefecture. He moved to the United States in 1904 where he resided in the San Francisco Bay area and worked in Sacramento and Placerville, California. After World War II he resettled in Los Angeles, California. Materials in this collection include diaries, memoirs, correspondence, and business and professional records related to the Akahori family. There are English and Japanese materials in this collection.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Akahori family papers (Collection 2010)
  - Akahoshi Papers, 1966; 1 folder
    Akahoshi Rihei (1878- ). A native of Kumamoto Prefecture who arrived in Victoria B.C. in 1900. A longtime resident in Seattle, Washington. Known as Rihei Bordeax.
    - My life story, translated by S. Hokama., 1966; (Manuscript, 14pp., 1 item) (Box 159, Folder 2)
  - Anderson Papers, 1944-1950; 0.5 linear ft.
    Hugh Harris Anderson was a member of the Friends of the American Way and the Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play. He assisted Japanese Americans in Southern California at the time of the forced removal and post-World War II resettlement. He also served as advisor in the Colorado River Relocation Center in Poston, Arizona. The collection consists of correspondence, documents, and miscellaneous printed materials related to Anderson's involvement with the activities of the Friends of the American Way and the incarceration of Japanese Americans during World War II.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Hugh H. Anderson papers (Collection 2010).
  - Anonymous Manuscripts, v.d.; 6 folders
    - Shiatoru kanzekai yurai [characters] [A history of the Seattle Kanzekai]. )., 1964; (Manuscript, 3pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 1)
    - Meiso no kiro ni tatsu kyojumin [characters] [Bewildered residents in the Granada Relocation Center], Amache, Colorado., n.d.; (8pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 2)
    - Untitled. A history of the Japanese agricultural colony in Cortez, California, 1919-ca. 1959., n.d.; (Manuscript, 14pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 3)
      Also, biographical sketches of prominent and longtime residents in the colony.
    - Jichi chiho hattenshi [characters] [A chronology of the development of the Japanese community in Gresham, Oregon]., n.d.; (Manuscript, 3pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 4)
    - Kyfu ter [characters] [Fear and terror]., ca. 1956; (Manuscript, 45pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 5)
      A psychological analysis of racial prejudice.
    - What some of our neighbors are doing about race relations., March 1945; (Manuscript, 4pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 6)
  - Anonymous Papers, 1924-1926; 2 folders
    Donors unknown.
    - Documents regarding the Hopland Incident., 1924; (14 documents) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Documents regarding the Hanford Incident., 1924 (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Documents regarding the J. Okamura Incident, Tulare County., 1926; (2 documents) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - A copy of a letter, the Yu-Ai-Kai [The Laborer's Friendly Society of Japan] to Samuel Gompers., (2pp., 1 item) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Reasons Why the Alien Land Law Should Be Revised., (Manuscript, [16pp.], 1 item) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - Yamato Ichihashi, Americanizing the Japanese (Efforts made by their own leaders)., n.d.; (Manuscript, 3pp., 1 item) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - K.K. Kawakami, Reconciling California Labor to the Japanese., n.d.; (Manuscript, [14pp.], 1 item) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - A statistical table showing the number of American-born Japanese who relinquished Japanese nationality, before June 17, 1924., (1p., 1 item) (Box 158, Folder 4)
      Compiled for the areas under the jurisdiction of the Consulate General of San Francisco.
    - Newspaper clippings from Japanese and English language press on Japanese citizenship., 1924; (4 pieces) (Box 158, Folder 4)
    - A woodblock print by Hiroshige., n.d.; (1 item) (Box 158, Folder 5)
  - Arai Family Papers, 1877-1972; 40.5 linear ft.
    Ryichir Arai was born in 1855 and came to New York in 1876 to start the direct export of silk. Ryichir Arai, Toyo Morimura, and Morimoto Sato were founders of Japanese American Trade, and they promoted closer relations between Japan and the United States. Yoneo Arai, son of Ryichir Arai, has served as Resident Representative of The Tokio Marine & Fire Insurance Company, Ltd. United States Fire Branch, a director of Japan Society, Vice president of the Japan Society, and Chairman of the Board, Yamaichi Securities Company of New York., Inc. The collection consists of personal and business papers of Ryichir Arai and his son, Yoneo Arai. They also include Arai family photographs. Portions of this collection are in Japanese.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Arai family papers (Collection 2010)
  - Ashizawa Papers, 1965-1989; 1.0 linear ft. (Box 152)
    Ashizawa was a native of Yamaguchi Prefecture who arrived in San Francisco, California, in 1899. He was a photographer and was also known as George Asher. Collection consists of sketches, photographs, glass plate negatives, and miscellaneous materials related to the life and career of photographer Riichi Ashizawa. Includes photographs of San Francisco, California, and of Japanese in the United States (ca. 1898-1920).
    For additional source see online finding aid: Riichi Ashizawa papers (Collection 2010)
  - Austin Papers, 1943-1945; 2.5 linear ft.
    Austin was born in 1894. He was Commander of the 752nd Military Police Battalion of Tule Lake, California from 1943-45. He retired from the U.S. Army as a Lieutenant Colonel. Collection contains records of events and exhibits related to the incarceration of Japanese Americans at Camp Tule Lake, California between October 1943 and October 1945. Includes copies of official files, biographical materials related to Col. Verne Austin and personal correspondence. Also contains scattered issues of the following newspapers published in the Tule Lake Relocation Center: The Tulean Dispatch, Newell Star, and Tsurureiki Shimp. Materials in this collection are primarily in English, with some in Japanese.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Verne Austin papers (Collection 2010)
  - Barnhart Papers, 1942-1954; 3.5 linear ft.
    Edward Norton Barnhart was a professor of Rhetoric at the University of California, Berkeley and also served as bibliographer for the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Collection there. This collection consists of copies and originals of reports, research papers, and publications related to the Japanese American Evacuation and Resettlement Collection Study and includes War Relocation Authority (WRA) publications and statistical reports on forced removal and resettlement. The collection also includes correspondence of the Tajiris mostly related to the Pacific Citizen and a small collection of personal records of Peruvian Japanese and their families incarcerated at Santa Fe and Crystal City. Materials in this collection are primarily in English with some in Japanese.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Edward N. Barnhart papers (Collection 2010)
  - Carr Papers, 1941-1962; 8.0 linear ft.
    Carr was a real estate agent in Pasadena, California, who founded the Friends of the American Way in February 1944 with a group of Pasadena residents and served as the organization's first chairman. The Friends of the American Way worked towards the restoration of the civil rights of Japanese Americans. He also founded the Pasadena Chapter of the Pacific Coast Committee on American Principles and Fair Play. He helped many Japanese American families during the time of incarceration and resettlement. The collection consists of correspondence, pamphlets, leaflets, reports, clippings, and other printed materials related to William C. Carr and the activities of the Friends of the American Way. Carr's correspondence with various state and local officials includes Earl Warren, Chester F. Gannon, Fletcher Bowron, Lloyd W. Lowrey, and Fred N. Howser. The collection also includes various samples of printed hate materials opposing the return and resettlement of Japanese Americans at the end of World War II. Includes reports and printed materials related to the War Relocation Authority (WRA).
    For additional source see online finding aid: William C. Carr papers (Collection 2010)
  - Chino Papers, 1921-1964; 1 folder and 1 oversize box
    Chino Tsuneji [characters] (1881-1964). Farmer, Southern California. A native of Nagano Prefecture. Arrived in the United States in 1905. Prominent in agricultural and other community organizations, and active in the legal battle against the 1913 & 1920 California Alien Land Laws.
    - Chino Tsuneji shi rireki gaiy [characters] [A short biographical sketch of Mr. Tsuneji Chino]., n.d.; (Manuscript, 29pp., 1 item) (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Tsuneji Chino. The end of the enforcement of the California Alien Land Law, translated by Mark Yoshio Kamii., 1960; (Manuscript, 25pp. + appendix. Ditto, 1 item). (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Photographs., ca. 1920-ca. 1924; (8 pieces) (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings., 1963-1964; (8 pieces) (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - JARP correspondence with the Chinos., 1963-1964; (7 letters) (Box 153, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper clippings about Chino Tsuneji, mostly in Japanese., 1958-1964; (2 oversize scrapbooks) (Box 726)
  - Chuman Papers, ca. 1900-ca. 1993; 98.0 linear ft.
    Chuman, a Nisei, was born in California in 1917. He graduated from the University of California, Los Angeles (1938) and the University of Maryland Law School (1945). He was the administrator at the Manzanar Camp hospital from 1942-43. He later was legal counsel for the National Japanese American Citizens League (JACL) from 1953-60 and served as its national president from 1960-62. He became a liaison to the Japanese American Research Project (JARP) in 1962 and published a book titled, The Bamboo People: The Law and Japanese Americans (c. 1976). The collection consists of correspondence, research notes, proofs, office files, and photographs related to the life and research of Frank F. Chuman. Also includes photographs of Manzanar Relocation Center in California and office files related to redress for Japanese American incarcerees. Other files contain materials related to Chuman's role as legal advisor to Little Tokyo Towers and the Little Tokyo Redevelopment Project. Portions of this collection are in Japanese.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Frank F. Chuman papers (Collection 2010).
  - DeForest Papers, 1942-1945; 6 folders and 1.0 linear ft.
    Charlotte B. DeForest. Biography unknown.
    - Manuscripts, 1 folder
      - Charlotte B. DeForest, Case work at Manzanar War Relocation Center., n.d.; (Manuscript, 10 pp.) (Box 153, Folder 2)
      - Charlotte B. DeForest, Closing out Manzanar: Ralph P. Merritt as I know him., n.d.; (Manuscript, 35 pp.) (Box 153, Folder 2)
    - Documents regarding the Manzanar War Relocation Center, California., 5 folders and 1 oversize box
      - DeForest's interview records and notes on incarcerees at Manzanar., July-December 1944; (Manuscripts, 12 items) (Box 153, Folder 3)
      - War Relocation Authority (WRA) staff memoranda and circulars., October 1944-November 1945; (39 items) (Box 153, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous items regarding the Manzanar Relocation Center., (28 items) (Box 153, Folder 5)
      - Agenda of Conference on Interracial Coordination, San Francisco., January 10-11, 1945; (Manuscript, 3 pp.) (Box 153, Folder 6)
      - Detroit Relocation Committee for Americans of Japanese Ancestry, Minutes of the meeting., June 7, 1946; (3pp., mimeographed) (Box 153, Folder 6)
      - Printed material. (Box 153, Folder 7)
        - Charlotte B. DeForest, Kobe College Alumnae in America 1942. Auburndale, Massachusetts., December 1942; (Newsletter) (Box 153, Folder 7)
        - Ferne Downing, editor, Cactus Blossoms 1945. Rivers, Arizona., (Mimeographed) (Box 153, Folder 7)
          A collection of poems written by students of Butte High School, Gila Relocation Center.
        - Ribsu kirisuto kykai shh [characters] [Rivers Tidings], no.58-59., January 21 & 28, 1944; (2 issues) (Box 153, Folder 7)
          Weekly bulletins of the Rivers Christian Church.
        - Manzanar Magpie., November 20 & December 21, 1944; and January 18, February 26 & April 21, 1945; (5 incomplete issues) (Box 153, Folder 7)
          Bulletins issued by the WRA staff of the Manzanar Relocation Center.
      - Mementos of the Manzanar Relocation Center., 1944-1945; (1 scrapbook) (Box 726)
  - Dimon Papers, 1942-1943; 2.5 linear ft.
    The W. Eugene Dimon papers contain newsletters, correspondence, albums and artifacts created by the Japanese who were detained at the Pomona Assembly Center in California from May to August 1942 and then transferred to the Heart Relocation Center in Wyoming in August 1942. The items were collected by W. Eugene Dimon, the Recreation Director of the Pomona Assembly Center.
    For additional source see online finding aid: W. Eugene Dimone papers (Collection 2010).
  - Fujii Papers, n.d.; 1 folder
    Fujii Chojiro [characters] (1878- ). Hotel owner, Seattle, Washington. A native of Hiroshima Prefecture who came to the United States in 1894. A longtime resident of Seattle.
    - 2 manuscripts of Fujii. (Box 160, Folder 7)
      - Shiyatoru-shi Nikkeijin keiei hoteru apto gy no hatten gairyakushi [characters] [A brief history of the development of Japanese hotel-apartment business in Seattle]., n.d.; (Manuscript, 13pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 7)
      - Sasaki Tokujiro [characters] [A short biographical sketch of Sasaki Tokujiro]., n.d.; (Manuscript, 7pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 7)
  - Fujioka Papers, 1954-1959; 1.0 linear ft.
    Fujioka was born in 1878 a native of Aomori Prefecture. He arrived in the United States in 1897 and attended Columbia University. He was a journalist for various Japanese language newspapers in the United States, including the Nyyku Shimp (New York Shimpo), the Hokubei Jiji (The North American Times) (Seattle), and the Rafu Shimp (The Los Angeles Japanese Daily) (Los Angeles). He was also an author and a respected spokesman and leader for the Southern California Japanese community before World War II. The collection consists of research data, biographical sketches, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other materials assembled by Fujioka for a series of articles entitled "Ayumi no ato" ("Traces of a Journey") which he wrote for the Rafu Shimp 1954-56. These articles were later published as a book under the same title in 1957 by Ayumi no Ato Kank Kenkai [Committee for the Publication of Ayumi no Ato], Los Angeles. Materials in this collection are primarily in Japanese, with some in English.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Shiro Fujioka papers (Collection 2010)
  - Hachimonji Papers, 1918-1955; 1.5 linear ft.
    Kumezo Hachimonji was born in 1888. A native of Miyagi Prefecture, he graduated from Thoku Gakuin in Sendai and arrived in the United States in 1918. He received his BS from Columbia University. Before World War II he owned and operated Valley Seed Company in El Monte, California. He was also known as K. Hatchmonji. The collection consists of diaries, essays, memoirs, correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, photographs, and photographic negatives related to the life of agricultural specialist and merchant Kumezo Hachimonji. Materials in the collection are in English and Japanese.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Kumezo Hachimonji papers (Collection 2010)
  - Hanaya Papers, n.d.; 1 folder
    Koan Hanaya [characters]. Hawaii-born Nisei and itinerant railroad laborer in Idaho, Montana, Nevada, and Utah.
    - Wakushi no ayunda michi [characters] [My past]., (Manuscript, 42pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 8)
      An incomplete autobiographical account.
  - Hibi Papers, 1893-1972; 29.5 linear ft.
    This collection consists of correspondence, exhibition catalogs, a scrapbook, sketches, watercolors, drawings, oil paintings, and monotype prints by Issei artist Matsusabur Hibi. Many of these materials relate to the time Hibi spent in the Tanforan Assembly Center (California) and the Central Utah Relocation Center in Topaz, Utah, during World War II. The collection also contains a portfolio of 50 scenes of the Central Utah Relocation Center drawn by Henry Fukuhara. There are English and Japanese materials in this collection.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Matsusabur Hibi papers (Collection 2010)
  - Hidekawa Papers, 1961; 1 folder
    Hidekawa Motohiko [characters]. Biography unknown.
    - Short biographical sketches of members of the Okayama Prefectural Association of San Francisco and a list of its officers before World War II., 1961; (Manuscript, 4pp., 1 item) (Box 160, Folder 9)
  - Higa Papers, 1944-1964; 1 folder
    Thomas Tar Higa, a Hawaiian-born Kibei, was born in 1916. He was a member of the 100th Infantry Battalion. The collection consists of documents of Higa's speech tour (1944) sponsored by the Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), photocopies of newspaper articles written by Higa and a copy of a privately printed pamphlet by Yasusato Sadao on the clothing relief drive for Okinawa in Hawaii titled Hawai ni okeru Okinawa hifuku kysai und no dki to sono kiroku (1964). Materials in this collection are primarily in Japanese, with some in English.
    For additional source see online finding aid: Tar Higa papers (Collection 2010).
  - Hoshimiya Family Papers, 1910-1968; 7.0 linear ft.